<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adams garden A meditation of thankfulnesse and praises vnto the Lord, for the returne and restore of Adam and his posteritie: planted as flowers in a garden, and published by a gentle-man, long exercised, and happilie trained in the schoole of Gods afflictions.</title>
            <author>Savile, Thomas, fl. 1595-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11536)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 774:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adams garden A meditation of thankfulnesse and praises vnto the Lord, for the returne and restore of Adam and his posteritie: planted as flowers in a garden, and published by a gentle-man, long exercised, and happilie trained in the schoole of Gods afflictions.</title>
                  <author>Savile, Thomas, fl. 1595-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Haueland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A gentle-man, long exercised, and happilie trained in the schoole of Gods afflictions" = Thomas Savile.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Goodness --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Adams Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A MEDITATION OF thankfulneſſe and praiſes vnto the Lord, for the returne and reſtore of <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſteritie: planted as flowers in a garden, and publiſhed by a Gentle-man, long exerciſed, and happilie trained in the ſchoole of Gods afflictions.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Abacuck</hi> 2.4.</bibl>
               <p>Behold, ſaith the Lord, he that exalteth himſelfe, his minde is not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: but the gentle and meeke is bleſſed, and hee ſhall inherite the earth. <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.5.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaiah</hi> 1.18.19.</bibl>
               <p>Come now, and let vs reaſon together, ſaith the Lord: If thou conſent and obay, thou ſhalt eat the good things of the land.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaiah</hi> 40.30.31.</bibl>
               <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euen the yong men, that put confidence in their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtrength; thoſe ſhall faint and bee wearie, euen the yong men ſhall ſtumble and fall.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Haueland.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND RENOWNED,</hi> George, <hi>Earle</hi> of Downbarre: <hi>Lord</hi> Howme of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke: <hi>Lord</hi> Norham: <hi>Lord-High-Treaſurer</hi> of Scotland: One of the <hi>Lords Lieutenants</hi> of the middle ſhires of great <hi>Britaine: Lord-Gouernour</hi> of the Towne and Garriſon of <hi>Berwicke: Knight</hi> of the moſt <hi>Honorable</hi> order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and one of the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Maieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies</hi> moſt <hi>Honorable</hi> priuie counſell in both Kingdomes:</head>
            <head type="sub">Thomas <hi>Sauile</hi> wiſheth all true Honour and <hi>Magnanimitie of mind, in the courſe of his Rule and</hi> Eſtate; which may be a perpetuall peace vnto his deſires.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your <hi>Lord-ſhip,</hi> I was bold (of late) to preſent you a little pamphlet of my writing; which you did pleaſe ſo verie fauourablie to accept (with declaration of your happie delight in ſuch things) as hath incouraged me to rippe vp all my faculties, and deepeſt comprehenſions, to offer your <hi>Lord-ſhip</hi> a further view, of ſuch my poore bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted gatherings, as may ſort to the ſame end with the former. Verie great ſurelie, is the loue and ſeruice I owe your moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> ſelfe, and euer muſt: For whether I regard, the wonderfull degrees of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,
<pb facs="tcp:6608:3"/>gentle (and not vainelie exalted minde) in ſpeeches, and affoorded graces by countenance and acceptation; or that which is much more, your open hand and purſe vnto my fainting eſtate (a fauour which I proteſt, I neuer taſted from any other <hi>Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of the world:) for my good <hi>Lord,</hi> it is wel knowne till of late yeeres, that my times haue beene diſpoſed and ſpent in giuing and not taking. I muſt therefore and doe deuote my ſelfe, to loue and admire your <hi>Lord-ſhip</hi> before the reſt. Bee pleaſed therefore (my beneficiall <hi>Lord</hi>) to receiue this poore pawne of my reſigned affections; and take view how ſtrange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations the Lord quilteth vpon the orphaned, ſuch as hee doth correct; euen to make them finde light in darkneſſe, and much confidence of reioicing in their forſaken and abandoned eſtate. I am bold to put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Lord-ſhip,</hi> the broydure of not being vainelie exalted; a true note of your wiſdome, and that you know your ſelfe, ſtate and calling, (and whatſoeuer in this mortalitie) fading, euen in Kings and Monarchs of the earth, the period vncertaine of diſſolution: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if the Lord ſhould afford you all the works of his hands, in full fruition, and withdraw his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſence from you; all you enioy in the world, ſhall bee found but comfortleſſe comforts, when the change (which certainelie doth attend all mortalitie) ſhall bee deſigned. It is the heart that the Lord reſpecteth and accepteth; and being reſigned and ankored in his will, hee will loue and eſtabliſh the proceedings thereof, for his verie owne delight in what alteration or change ſoeuer: So that what ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, trouble, greefe or croſſe, may befall you, they
<pb facs="tcp:6608:3"/>ſhall but be as his meſſengers, to bring you a ſeale and aſſurance of his fatherlie indulgence and care; and that hee will haue your heart himſelfe in keeping (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe with him there is no change at all) and ſo will build you vp, vnto that aſſurance of hopefull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, wherein you ſhall find prepared, all peace, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, perſeuerance, and what in the world may bee moſt deſired, for the type of euer-during feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city: which the Lord in all his fauourable enlargements giue you. And ſo I praie pardon.</p>
            <p>A gentle-man long trained in her late Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, vnder that euer famous Lord-Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Now your Lord-ſhips faithfull ſeruant <hi>Thomas Sauile.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y kind gentle <hi>Reader,</hi> wee ſay in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes terpriſes and preuailings of <hi>Armes,</hi> ſuch a Captaine did ſuch a ſeruice, where not the commander, hut the Souldiers did the atchieue. I now in this booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <hi>Adams</hi> returne, by a contrarie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert; where not <hi>Adams</hi> progenie but <hi>Adam</hi> alone made the breach, by open offence; yet the penaltie ſorteth vpon all his attainted poſteritie by propagation and line of blood: and as his guilt is theirs, ſo his returne deſcendeth vnto them, as the ſouldiers bee ſharers in the Captaines preuail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. This exerciſe therefore I call <hi>Adams Garden,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proceedeth from the reſtored Armie of his peculiar quarter, by the happie <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> euen by his renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affordings, who is the <hi>Creator, Reſtorer,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer of the whole attaindor.</hi> It is not needleſſe, but (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) verie needfull, that men ſhould dwell in deepe cogitation thereof, and ſtill exerciſe their thoughts in the wonderfull diſperſed ſtorme of ſuch a penaltie, to the end the Crowne of ſo bountifull receiued enlargement, might more ſenſiblie ſettle in their hard and vnprepared faculties. Oh that ſame Cenſure of a Father, touching fruition of our periſhing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights: Oh, I ſay, that it might bee as trulie verified vpon our often meditation of <hi>Adams</hi> happie returne, by dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the gardens of our open acknowledgements for the Lords exceeding patience, to pardon, call, and enforce our
<pb facs="tcp:6608:4"/>fathers happie repaire! His words be theſe: <hi>Facilè enim cor humanum, omnibus quae frequentat, adhaeret ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, vt vix aut nunquam ſine amore valcant poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri.</hi> So I wiſh that our frequent dwelling in thankefull care and obedience might once beget the ſetled zeale and ſtable wreſtling ſtrife of loue and admiration in vs, for ſo high ſhrined a ſtate and prerogatiue, by reſtoring and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning. But wofull, and ſtrong, and reſiſting, is that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued nature, and combat from our firſt ſtirpe, for vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things; and too too ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> to ſubſcribe the ſighings of the ſpirite and gronings of grace in vs, to enioy the birth of a more holie renewment. Our deſires bee called the birth of the ſoule, and the creations of God, which ſhall not periſh. But how ſhould wee aſſure our ſelues heereof? being ſtill dull, dead, and ſo ſlow, to ſtriue for our crowne: wee haue all the encouragement that a graceleſſe froward creature can require: wee haue God to prepare our hearts and heare vs: <hi>Pſal. 10. ver. 17.</hi> wee haue Ieſus Chriſt to receiue and embrace vs: <hi>Matt. 11. ver. 28.</hi> wee haue the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter to lead vs aright: <hi>Ioh. 14.</hi> to aske and preſent our deſines, from his owne vnſpeakable ſighings and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; becauſe wee know not what to aske as wee ought: Whereupon another Father calleth our praiers, <hi>Arma cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>: qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtare nos faciunt, et fortiter perſeuerare: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>nt manimenta ſpiritualia &amp; tela diuina:</hi> becauſe our pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s bee not ours, but the vehement deſires of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. As for vs; <hi>Quod poſtulamus, idem ipſe donat, qui dat vt poſtulemus.</hi> Alacke, that wee haue no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to hold faſt and enioy the Lords gentleneſſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie with vs. What are we, if he pleaſe to depart from vs, and leaue vs to an accuſing conſcience? nay, what is the greateſt Menarch in the world? Oh heauy ſtate well known
<pb facs="tcp:6608:5"/>vnto manie! and in mercie ſomething vnto the author heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. If the Lord doe ſet vp but one of our ſinnes to purſue vs, nay but one of our cogitations to accuſe vs, and depart from vs; wee ſhall find ſuch a flame of burning, vnreſt, &amp; torment in our thoughts, as to beſeech him returne againe and helpe vs, and take from vs all thoſe worldlie priorities and ſhrined vanities of our abundance,, which haue ſeduced and ſnared our faculties, in verie eminent and high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of conſuming torments: But men bee ſecure, and by fulneſſe and immunities, their diſeaſe is growne ſo remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, as hardlie to beleeue there can bee any ſuch miſerie in mortalitie. But I chooſe rather to lament their eſtate, then conuince their preſumptuous opinions; and therefore will cut off, and leaue all redreſſe vnto him that is both able and willing, to worke for his owne; and will call in his time thoſe that bee appointed, by what motion, change, or croſſe ſoeuer may pleaſe him beſt. To this gentle mercifull Lord, I doe recommend thee patient <hi>Reader,</hi> and this my poore labour, as a ſeruice to ſuperionrs; my loue to equals and familiars; and a compaſsionate well wiſhing vnto all that loue the comming of the Lamb, euen the Lord Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:5"/>
            <head>The Contents of the booke in generall.</head>
            <p>The former booke of Adams returne, doth conſiſt of open acknowledgements, vnfolding the ſecret ſtill liuing preſumption and inherent leproſie in his poſteritie: which (to auoid diſtaſte) the Author acteth in his owne rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſelfe, reſembling <hi>Dauids</hi> pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall, &amp; ſorrowing Pſalmes of humiliation.</p>
            <p>This garden doth by open ſhew, enlarge and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, ſuch exerciſes and renewed effects of the happie returne, as the writer did receiue from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; the Lord pleaſed to afford vnto him from cogitation and admiration of ſo happie a change:</p>
            <p>Reſembling <hi>Dauids</hi> illumination and cheered eſtate of thankefulneſſe, in his Pſalmes of conſolation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gather flowers of each rowe ſome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And make a poſie' gainſt Maſter come:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And hee will ſmile vpon thy choice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thanke thee with a gentle voice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ableſſed thing to make him ſmile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who neuer heere in his exile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For thirtie yeeres did one ſmile ſhew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let him now ſee thy Lilies grow.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6608:6"/>
            <head>ADAMS GARDEN.</head>
            <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my moſt mercifull Lord, who haſt enforced my returne, after my running away from thee, euen by the call of thy tender compaſſions, whereby I was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully affrighted &amp; confounded, out of mine owne guiltie wounded conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for diſobaying thy word; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by loſing thy freelie beſtowed glorious garden vpon mee: and now at the laſt, doeſt exerciſe me in my deſires of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience, for ſo great a fauour and deliuerance recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; to plant and preſent (for thy delight) euen a new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Garden, (far exceeding that of <hi>Eden</hi>) out of the choice of thine owne created flowers in my verie ſinnefull heart, where thou haſt pleaſed to leaue, ſome little ſparks of the firſt creation.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Good Lord helpe mee, to plant, to ſquare, and frame eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie quarter; in ſuch ſeemelie ſort and proportion, as beeing furniſhed with varietie of thy ſweete and fragrant created flowers, I may pleaſe thee, and vndergoe my calling, to digge and delue ſtill, by penaltie from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and may bee acceptable and delightfull vnto thee, in and by the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> euen to make an habitation, where thou and the Lambe may pleaſe to dine, and ſup, and euen dwell ſtill.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6608:7"/>
            <p n="3">III. Nothing is hid from thee, thou readeſt in the tables of my heart, and well ſeeſt how my compunction, and ſorrow for abuſing thy fauours, euen load and preſſe mee downe: yet heerein bee pleaſed, to enlarge my cheere and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that much greater is the glorie of my returne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, then was the fruition of <hi>Eden</hi> to <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. For therein, as wofully appeareth, I had power to loſe, both garden and bleſſing; and indeed was no more but a priueledged creature for a time, made of clay, duſt, and the baſeſt earth; but now thou haſt otherwiſe bewtified and ſhrined mee, by thy loue vnto mee.</p>
            <p n="5">V. And of thy free mercie and gratious bountie, now haſt giuen mee a dignitie, prioritie, and priueledge; whereby I am not onelie ſet free, from ſatans ſubduings, the worlds ſnarings, &amp; deaths wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings, (to hinder my now happy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; progreſſe) but am in thoſe combats of theirs, made an open co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queror ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al: for thou haſt affoorded me a dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, farre exceeding my firſt Creation: So that I cannot be mooued, though I bee ſhaken and toſſed, to trie my victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ouer them: for what conqueſt, without oppoſition and combate?</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Now I can loſe my kindred and garden no more: Now I can fall finallie no more: I can loſe my vnion with Chriſt Ieſus no more, nor bee ſeparated from him any more: So true it is, that whom thou calledſt, thou haſt iuſtified and glorified: whereby, I am in thee ſo highlie aduanced; as not onelie to bee Lord of all the workes of thy hand; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror of all enmitie ariſing againſt thy bleſſed will: yea,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6608:7"/>euen of that propoſed enmitie, which muſt continue till there bee no more time.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. So that, not onelie his deſcending and death is mine; but his Riſing and Aſcending alſo: yea his verie righteouſneſſe, is mine by imputation; whereby I am able to ſatisfie the whole lawe, out of my owne crucified fleſh, in and by him who loueth mee. Who or what ſhall I feare now? ſince all the world trembleth at his voice, who ſpeaketh and ruleth, out of my verie fleſh.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. O mercifull Lord, bowe downe and heare my crie and ſighes, for obedience and humilitie, that the knowledge of this happie vnion, make me not bold, but onlie in the cauſes of thy glorie, againſt that deuouring Satan, that I may once deale large ſpoiles, from that conqueſt which thou wilt giue mee ouer him, euen for thy names ſake, and in fauour of this thy new reconcilement and couenant, which thou haſt made betwixt thy Chriſt and my ſinnefull ſoule.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. For alaſſe, hee ſmarteth when I draw penaltie vpon me by diſobedience: In all my troubles he greeueth with mee and is troubled with mee. For ſo long as this vnion laſteth (which is foreuer) that Chriſt Ieſus is my head and I his member, how can it bee, but hee endureth my miſerie euen with mee.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Oh wonderfull and vnſpeakable bountie! a ſecret hidde from many. Hee hath not onelie made mee Lord ouer the whole earth, but by his conſecration hath communicated his glorious and paſſible ſpirit, to bee wounded for my declinings. Oh hearts of men and women, where be they?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6608:8"/>Oh, that loue of <hi>Marie</hi> was great and ſweete: Tell me, ſaith ſhe, where they haue laide him, that I may fetch him. Oh ſeeking, Oh hungrie, Oh bedroughted zeale, to drinke deep in the fountaine of his vnſpeakable kindneſſe! <hi>Marie,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>Rabbonie,</hi> ſaith ſhe: Oh harmonie! indeede ſweete har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: <hi>Seeke thou my face: I will ſeeke thy face O Lord. Pſ. 27</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">XI. O Lord increaſe my faith, that once I may be ſwallowed vp, by ſenſe and ſweete power of thy ſauing health; let it conuince and mollifie my ſtonie and drowſie heart, by thy helpe O Lord; and let euen ſhame driue mee into admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy exceeding compaſſions. For, haſt thou not O Lord, made thy ſelfe my moſt mercifull father? Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus my happie Redeemer? The Holie Ghoſt my euer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Comforter? The Angels my miniſtring ſpirits? All thy creatures my ſeruants? The earth my ſoiourning place? &amp; the heauens for my home? What couldeſt thou haue done more to thy friend? and yet I liue at a wofull enmitie with thee, and by open frailties am euen enuious of thy glorie.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Oh how trulie (though moſt vnworthily) may I ſay againe and againe, all the workes of Gods hands be mine, and I am Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods, to the euerlaſting glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of his grace and goodneſſe? and yet I ſinne ſtill, prouoke him ſtill, and euen crucifie the Lambe ſtill, &amp; make the Comforter weepe ſtill: For to dwell in my former diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, what elſe is it, but euen to call Chriſt againe vnto death, and euen fight againſt his Reſurrection?</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Alas for pittie, that neither the experience of his goodnes will hold mee in obedience, nor the feare of his greatnes rouſe mee from ſecuritie. Returne O Lord and bee mightie in mee, for thy names ſake: Let thy face ſhine vpon mee,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6608:8"/>let thy preſence breath life and ſtrength into mee, that <hi>I</hi> may bring glorie vnto thy name, in making knowne by the moderate and holie vſe of this my life, that it is another life I looke and attend for; in regard whereef I deſire to be ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of all thoſe impediments (how delightfull ſoeuer vnto nature) that may debar and ſtop my neere familiaritie, with thee moſt mercifull Lord, and the gentle Jeſus, by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Comforter.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Oh that I could find the ſtate of my happineſſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy promiſes, and bee more deeplie touched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and ſing with <hi>Ezekias: The Lord hath ſaide it, and the Lord hath done it.</hi> Hee hath knitte the care of his people, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the glorie of his name; and for my encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and comfort, profeſſed, that as hee will not giue his glorie and name to be polluted; no more will he forget to ſhew mercie vnto his people, euen vnto me.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Renew mee therfore O Lord for this thy names ſake, and eſtabliſh a right and ſtable iudgement in me of this thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and when thou haſt renewed mee, doe not then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee forſake me; but put a bridle in my mouth to the end I may by abſtinence, keepe my ſelfe in modeſtie and feare, ouer my euill heart; and free mee from ſurfetings and vaine perſwaſions, which pricke mee forward to voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, that in a godlie care to ſerue thee, ſtill admiring thy face, which beholdeth me continuallie in all my waies, I may zealouſhe ſet ſpurres to the flankes of my ſlothfull and impure negligence, to awake and rouze mee from ſecure ſleeping and ſitting in thy diſpleaſure, with this careleſſe and vnreformed world.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Appeaſe therefore all countenance of thy Iudgments (for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6608:9"/>paſſed offences) O mercifull Lord; and now be pleaſed that I deale with thee vpon a new couenant, to ſeale vp the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of my intereſt in thy promiſes, euen in a deuoted and reſigned preparation vnto thy will. I confeſſe that I haue deſerued moſt iuſtlie, to bee totallie and finallie caſt away, and raced out of the Record of the liuing: But ſeing J haue a long while called vpon thy goodneſſe; euen for thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding gentleneſſe, O Lord, I beſeech thee deliuer me from all thoſe euills which do enuiron me: For behold (my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord) I doe (thou knoweſt) lead my life in a moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull manner, for that I cannot ſerue thee as I would: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing but to pleaſe thee; and on the contrarie, my wicked nature luſteth continuallie to greeue thee. This I call and feele a moſt miſerable life, my gracious Lord, which receiue mercifullie into thy pittie, and redreſſe compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natelie of thy grace, euen when it may beſt pleaſe thee, for all thy mercies ſake.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. O mercifull Lord, who haſt vouchſafed to vnſeale the eies of my vnderſtanding, to ſee the myſterie of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Returne: make me O Lord to taſt the fruits thereof, which (flouriſhing vpon the tree of the croſſe) ſhall with the force thereof, quicken and giue life vnto my faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead ſoule. Preſerue and warrant me for euer from the ruine, which hath ſo miſerablie brought together the race of mankind, and ouerflowed them by diſobedience.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Eſtabliſh in my heart, O Lord my God, an habitation for thy holie Spirit; to the end I neuer heereafter, breath or vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forth any thing but tending to thy praiſes; and let thy will bee alwaies printed in my mind, and thy glorie grauen vpon my lippes, that my lippes being opened my mouth may ſhew forth thy praiſe.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6608:9"/>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>XIX.</hi> I doe humblie thanke thee my mercifull Lord, for my Election, Calling, Creation, Redemption, Regeneration, Iuſtification, Sanctification, Preſeruation, Glorification, Reſurrection, Righteouſnes: But moſt eſpeciallie, for that moſt ancient loue of thine, wherein thou haſt continuallie watched ouer mee, gathered me with thine arme, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me in thy boſome, in ſuch exceeding loue and care; as when <hi>I</hi> had beſtowed all my daies in open diſobedience, &amp; was vtterlie vndone by my fraile delights; euen then in a verie moment, thou brokeſt the heauens and ſcatteredſt the cloudes to come down and plucke me out of the mouth of the deuouring Dragon, taking mee by the hand, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing me this large time of repentance, to the end <hi>I</hi> ſhould declare thy name vnto my brethren.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>XX.</hi> Nay, my mercifull Lord, more then this, thou haſt not onely ſeene my vnrighteouſneſſe, and been patient euen to be prouoked by me, but haſt couered my open offences from the eies of men, and kept me reputed as vnſpotted and blameleſſe in the world, when many a time for my wilfulnes in many things thou mighteſt haue infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted an open and fearefull penalty vpon me: Thus moſt gratiouſly preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in thy vnſpeakeable fauour that the blemiſhes of my fraile youth, ſhould not ſcandall or defame thy calling, and the moſt humblie deſired Returne of my Age.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. It is verily true indeed that I haue ſinned moſt vnwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly and audaciouſly: I lay open vnto thee and the whole world the very bottome of my heart: Thou knoweſt my whole life, I haue ſinned in the ſight of Heauen and Earth, I will neuer ſtand in defence or pleade excuſe before thee,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6608:10"/>For my grace and pardon is in thy hand onely, and I looke for peace and redreſſe onely from thee.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. For thou haſt granted vnto me, behold a token of thy owne bloud ſealed in the image of my fleſh; which for my Redemption thou haſt imprinted in the weakeneſſe of my ſubſtance: So that now thou requireſt nothing but obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and loue; and alaſſe I grieue thee day by day, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thee day by day, and euen weary my ſelfe in the waies of darknes and ſhadow of death. And what haue I gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by al thoſe my careleſſe actions, and proceedings wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am now aſhamed?</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. Truely O Lord, I gaine euen this, to giue open ſentence againſt my ſelfe for abuſing thy mercies, and account my ſelfe that vntimely fruit that ſhameth the tree that bore it, and the earth which nurſed it, and the heauens which ripened it. Therefore O Lord I will take vp my Croſſe in penalty, and where others look for their fruit after the bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and blooming times, I will looke for mine after the fall of leafe: for after the leafe of this body ſhall be gathered, I hope that my ſoule ſhall budde in a new fruit and bee cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed againe with the Verdure of Immortality.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIIII. Behold therefore O Lord, that the open acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my ſinne, I preſently beare vpon my head &amp; as men who fetch water at a well doc put the mouth of the bucket downe, and cloſe it vp; ſo will I my gracious Lord keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vnto thee. For he that will aſcend muſt firſt fal downe, and to kiſſe the heauens, he muſt firſt kiſſe the earth, and he that will haue a Crown with God muſt be firſt beaten and wronged with men.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6608:10"/>
            <p n="25">XXV. And now my moſt gratious God, to the end I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſo honourably apparelled as ſuch a magnificence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to ſee immortality, I beſeech thee throw downe the huge mountaine of my ſinnes, and burie them in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of the earth, and ſeparate me for euer from mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which at this preſent I do repudiate, and ſweare a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall diuorce betweene them and my ſoule.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. Thou knoweſt moſt mercifull Lord, and haſt taught mee to know, that the humble and iuſt man is the very tutor of nature, reſtrayning and moderating all natural appetites by ſtability and wiſedome. And ſince I would thus preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature, wilt thou not, (O Lord) which vnderſtandeſt the bottomleſſe pitte of Hell, wilt thou not heare my poore fainting deſires, which by ſighing reacheth and beateth the heauens, and wherewith I haue long entreated thee? Shall all the world heare me but thy ſelfe alone? Oh no my God, thou haſt too long ſtretched out thine arme now to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect me, when J aske nothing but to glorifie thee.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. Alas my ſweet Lord, I haue ſetled my whole power and ſtrength vpon the loue and obedience of thy countenance, which I haue ſo many times prouoked: and if thou pleaſe not to aſſiſt me in this ſeruice, alas what manner of fight ſhall I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e able to make againſt the ſtrong enemies of my ſoule? O p ttifull pittifull will be my preuailings; nay my aſſured backſlidings. Say therefore vnto my ſoule, I will not faile thee, I hold thee by thy right hand, and thou ſhalt neuer be forſaken.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6608:11"/>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. Thou knoweſt, O Lord, men haue had mee in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard, and loe how now I am deſputed and befoiled with their ſcorne and contempt: for in ſtead of ſorrowing with me they haue coniured againſt me, and doe adde ſorrow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heauines, and make me a laughing ſtock and a matter of deriſion, ſaying, verily he can neuer rife. Again, He called vpon God very much indeed, and ſee what he hath gained. But I will be ſtill; for the daies be euill, and my ſilence ſhall ſpeake vnto thee by continuall deſires, ſighes and groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. Yet doe I not for all this loſe my hope; no no my good God, for thy power is infinit, and thy mercy vnmeaſurable, which wil ſpread it ſelfe euen as a roabe ouer ſuch as truſt in thee, and the Lambe ſhal know the roabe by thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therof, and ſhal ſay, thou art mine O deſpiſed Iacob, O thou Caſtaway Sion, whom no man regardeth: I haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee by thy name, thou art mine, feare not, thou ſhalt not periſh, though they fall on euery ſide of thee.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. Heereupon, mercifull Lord, I gather courage and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that thou haſt not lifted thy ſelfe vpon ſo high and eminent a place to diſmay thy ſeruants, but that they might ſee thy ouerruling power and hand of their propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation farre beyond the touch and controll of man, yea of al Monarchs, for the better aſſurance and confidence of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, for their reioycing and hope by the priority and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminency of their election: for they muſt follow the lamb and ſee his face, that their ioy may be full.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. O thou moſt mercifull Lord which doeſt not remember
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6608:11"/>wrongs, haſt ſeene the dangers which by violent ſway of ſinne I haue caſt my ſelfe into, forgetting all thy mercies, prouoking thy glorious face, traducing the Redeemer, and greeuing the Comforter: O returne and make haſt O Lord for my recuring and cleanſing from this huge prouocation, euen for thy gentlenes, and becauſe thou haſt ſpared mee thus long, and now beginneſt to touch my heart.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. I did neuer ſo ſoone thinke to confeſſe my ſinnes, but thou preſently gaueſt pardon: I did neuer ſo ſoone returne vnto thee as thou waſt ready to offer thy ſelfe vnto mee: I did neuer make open or ſecret acknowledgement of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued penalties, but thou didſt remit them preſently: I haue taken the rods to haue ſcourged my ſelfe, when thou haſt pluckt them out of my hand: I did thinke thou wouldſt haue proclaimed warres, and behold open peace and pardon brought me, with charge and truſt to trimme vp and keepe the manſion of my ſoule heereafter for thee, and to feare nothing but ſanctifie thy name in my heart; for thou wilt be a refuge vnto me, therefore I feare not all changes.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. Oh what an acceptable ſacrifice before thee is a broken and contrite heart, that out of the voice of a iuſt man paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth aboue the heauens, &amp; the ſweet ſighing comforter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the ſame before thee. This humble acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from a wounded heart in the ſinner wilt thou neuer reiect, becauſe thou findeſt in this ſtate the greeued image of the lambe, from which thou canſt neuer turne thy face.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIIII. And further, mercifull Lord, my hope receiueth good reliefe, becauſe the Saints (which are the holy men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6608:12"/>liuing) haue praied, doe pray and will pray for mee; thoſe are they which do beſeech thee for me. Oh it is time that they doe attend thee for me, ſince impiety of my hart hath ſo blinded my ſenſes by euill thoughts, that my ſoule cannot lift vp her ſelfe towards heauen, nor ſtretch out her hand vnto thee, who art onely both able and willing to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ranſome the Captiues that ſit in darkneſſe and deep diſcourage.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. Therefore haſt thou prouided that ſuch as thou vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeſt to come neere vnto thee by faith and holineſſe of life, may pray and beſeech thee, that thou wouldeſt ſatiſfie my ſoule, and purge my thoughts ſo preſeruing &amp; warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me foreuer from that ruine and calamitie which hath ſo miſerably imbondaged and pinioned together the race of tranſgreſſors, and holden them in irkeſome ſlauery, as chained and deſigned to a great and irkeſome Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. As for my ſelfe, who am mine owne Capitall enemy, I haue neuer had ſkill or will to pray for my treſpaſſes, but euen wandred in dreadfull expectation vnder a heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: yet heerein I am ſomewhat cheered, that by this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of my eſtate thou haſt let me ſee what a blacke and foule conſcience I haue, and haſt mollified my heart that I might lodge contrition in my ſoule, to obtaine grace and fauour with thee, that in thine owne time, merciful Lord, thou wilt pleaſe to purge and waſh it.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. Thou O my good God which haſt beene from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, art neuer changed, whereupon it is that wee bee not confounded, but art euer one and the ſame, without anie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6608:12"/>ſhadow of change: for age &amp; time which conſume al things, ſerue for no other purpoſe but to confirme thine euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſſe: and men ſeeme to remaine heere vpon earth, for no other cauſe, but to behold thy incomprehenſible great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; vnchangeable on the one ſide, and their certaine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, approching out of their mortalitie on the other ſide.</p>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. For a man changeth not his ſhirt ſo often, but the earth changeth her inhabitants more often; yet thou my God art euen the ſame at this day that thou wert at the firſt, which the heauens and earth continually ſing vnto thee; and that neither time paſt, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or to come, ſhall euer change thee.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Keepe mee therefore O Lord in a ſtable and ſober exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of my faith and aſſurance, that I do not wauer or ſhrink in the ſtormes of my mortalitie, neither deſpaire at any time, by ſenſe of apparances, or ſmart of feelings. For hee which deſpaireth for his ſin (vnleſſe thou pleaſe to deſigne that afflicto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by deſertion, to giue experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by) he euen doth giue ouer his ſoule as already condemned, and is like that abominable vſurer, who hauing ſuſtained ſome loſſe in his goods, by and by bereaueth himſelfe of his life alſo: Make thou therefore ſtrong ſteppes for my faith O Lord, that I neuer diſhonour thy name, by the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſleights of my ſenſes, but euen ſtand faſt armed with thy promiſes for euer.</p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>XL.</hi> And ſo prepare mee vnto the chaſtiſements of my peace (theſe ſame ſweete healing potions and appliances) that the ſmart thereof neuer driue me from thee; but euen rather as the laſhes light vpon mee, I may kiſſe the rod and ſay it is too little, for I haue deſerued much more, but that of thine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6608:13"/>owne indulgence and pitie thou ſpareſt me: Giue me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Lord to learne obedience by thy ſtripes; and moſt welcome and ſweete euen ſhall bee vnto mee thy afflictions, yea, euen the changes of my afflictions, the lot of thy children.</p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>XLI</hi> Thus inſtructing and nurtring mee in thy owne moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſchoole of diſcipline, let me feele O Lord thy wil, to take more rule and ſoueraignety ouer my will, then it hath done in former times, that I may taſt and experience that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which hee feeleth that is deliuered from the bond of captiuitie, and ſet at libertie out of priſonne and thraldome wherein his enemies had long held him chained.</p>
            <p n="42">
               <hi>XLII</hi> For thou haſt alreadie done verie much for my ſoule O Lord; thou haſt taken and held mee faſt by the hand in all my dangers, and ſet mee gentlie againe in the way of thy will, with greater compaſſion then euer <hi>Paul</hi> did embrace <hi>Eutychus,</hi> and madſt mee vnderſtand thy will and purpoſe: Nay thou haſt done more then that, for mee thinks thou haſt both opened mine eies and the heauens all at once, that I ſhould ſee the mightineſſe of thy glorie, as I do at this preſent ſenſiblie feele the goodneſſe of thy grace.</p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>XLIII</hi> Thou haſt O Lord made mee ſe, I ſay, the mightineſſe of that thy power, whereunto no mortall man can attaine without thee: for alaſſe, ſhould I poore ſillie worme thinke, that I am more then I am, to go to ſeeke for that in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens which I cannot well ſee at my feete? the eies of my body be duskie &amp; miſtie, and the eies of my ſoule be much worſe: but thou the mercifull Lord, delighteſt to bring light forth of darkneſſe for manifeſtation of thy power, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy bleſſed power.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6608:13"/>
            <p n="44">XLIV. And mens thoughts are maruellous vncertaine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering; for the earthlie and corruptible bodie, dulleth and maketh idle our ſpirits, and tieth and bindeth our ſenſes faſt to the earth: ſo that without thee my gentle Lord, I can hope for no light heere belowe, to know or diſcerne any thing aright: But Chriſt Ieſus is the way, the truth life and light, whoſe renewed obedience is ſtill fragrant in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; euen hee is my light and portion for euer.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. And by him moſt mercifull Lord, thou doeſt ſupplie my wants, and leadeſt mee by the hand to ſee the counſels of thy eternall wiſdome, and haſt heaued &amp; violently mooued my ſoule to make it capable, and ſenſiblie to feele thy light and commiſeration.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. Wherefore O Lord touching my enemies and thoſe who haue wrongfully oppreſſed mee, and cloſed mee in much obſcuritie and blemiſh of eſtate; I do humblie and with all my verie heart intreat thee for them, that thou pleaſe not to blow vpon them the wind and blaſt of thy curſe; but tarie ſweete Lord, if ſo it ſeeme good to thee, to ſee if thy patience will bring them to do their duties: nay rather draw them O Lord, to repent their cauſleſſe wrongs orphanings and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent outrage that they haue committed againſt me.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. And as for mee, though I bee couered ouer with their wounds, and defamed with their iniurious dealings; yet had I rather haue them ſubiect vnto thy mercie, then once to feele thy iudgement; and deſire of thee, if thou think good, that their vnmercifulneſſe vnto mee, might rather ſerue to trie mee withall, then for their condemnation.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6608:14"/>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. Thou knoweſt O Lord my deſires, &amp; takeſt view of them out of my moſt ſecret priuities and thoughts, and that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer called on thee for vengeance for my receiued wrong: No no, the feelings of thy mercies vnto my vnworthy ſelfe, make mee deepelie deſire to bee farre from thinking of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſmarts offered vnto me. Indeed moſt mercifull Lord, my vowes do importune nothing but thy mercies, and my thoughts are addreſſed vnto nothing but vnto peace, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled brotherlie fellowſhip.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. The verie end of all my deſires O Lord (if thou pleaſe I report it) is, that I may paſſe my daies in ſeruing thee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie, and that thou wouldeſt grant mee thy holie houſe to dwell in, euen in the congregation of thine owne choſen wife and ſpouſe the church; and that all the while I am ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from thee, and a great waie off from thy heauenly tabernacle, tied vnto the earth by reaſon of the counter poiſe of this my bodie, I might vnite and tie all my thoughts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, &amp; conforme my ſelfe whollie vnto thy moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous will.</p>
            <p n="50">L. Oh bleſſed habitation, that is able to couer mee from all worldlie paſſions, from all the luſts of the fleſh and aſſaults of Satan; for there O Lord thou art preſent with mee, and comeſt downe from the heauens to keepe companie with mee; and filleſt mee with thy ſelfe that I might bee fenced againſt ſinne, and this my carnall will, and conuerted into a heauenlie, liuing, and quickning ſpirite.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. That I may once feele effectually thy maruellous works, comprehend thy mercies, and conceiue of thy power and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6608:14"/>almightines: Reueale therefore vnto thy ſeruant this thy will, &amp; lay it vp in my heart, that I may there keepe it moſt deerelie, and in the midſt of thy church may ſet vp an altar vnto thee, euen in my mouth, for an offering, vnder the vaile of thy moſt holie word.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. And to this end O Lord, I beſeech thee helpe mee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie: for as mine infirmitie ſtriueth commonlie againſt mee, ſo alſo haue I neede of continuall helpe on euerie ſide: Therefore good Lord when thou haſt comforted mee, doe ſtill exerciſe mee and bee with mee, I beſeech thee, and tary with mee; knead, mould, and frame this lumpe of earth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thou wilt, to thine owne ſeruice and worſhip.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. And now my moſt mercifull Lord, hauing pleaſed thee, ſo as thou art reconciled with mee, and I with all mine heart reſigned vnto thee, euen to doe thy will: what ſhall I neede to feare, ſeeing all the world doth dread and fall down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee? that defendeſt thy ſeruants, and haſt aſſured mee to watch ſtill ouer mee euen night and daie, and keepe mee vnder the ſhadow of thine owne wings: thou wilt giue the angels charge ouer mee, that I hurt not my foote nor faint in my way, nor bee wearie in my iourney vnto thy holie hill.</p>
            <p n="54">LIIII. Thou art the mightie defender of the poore and orpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and who is able to reſiſt thy power? Thy forces O Lord are not armies of men, but Legions of Angels: thy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are not onelie Princes and Captaines, but thundrings, lightnings, and ſtormes: thy wrath is not blowes and hurts, but Earth-quakes, ſwallowing v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Cities and drowning of Countries; ſo triumphant, victorious, and glorious, art thou in all thy waies.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6608:15"/>
            <p n="55">LV. But my Lord, becauſe thou doeſt hold backe this thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing hand of power and maieſtie; comfort me ſtill with a ſure hope that thou wilt not forſake me, and giue me ſuch a meaſure of faith, as may lead mee vnto the hauen of thy promiſes, and therein compact mee as a ſtone well ſquared for the maſters building, ſited vpon <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> which ſhall neuer be remooued.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. And me thinks thou ſaieſt vnto me continually, tarie a little, for the time is not yet come that I haue appointed, &amp; in the meane while truſt thou aſſuredly vnto my promiſes, and looke whatſoeuer wrong, diſgrace or affliction, thou ſhalt beare, I will bee with thee, and giue thee ſtrength to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercom it: thou hauing learned <hi>that all things woorke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the beſt, to them that loue mee.</hi> I haue not laid thee in the fire to burne and conſume thee, but to fine thee, and make thee orient in my ſight, euen as the Diamond, by much and often rubbing is more beautifull.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. Heereby my courage (O Lord) encreaſeth, when I ſee my ſelfe thus ſeconded by thee; and this thy fauour and gentleneſſe, doth more embolden mee vnto patience, then all the applauſe of the people, doth him that fighteth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, when he is moſt ſtrong and luſtie in fight, and ſeeth the victorie alreadie by his fainting aduerſarie.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. Certainelie, I know the conſcience of an innocent man, that is founded and grounded vpon thy grace (my Lord) is more ſtable and ſure then all the greateſt rockes, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſhaken or mooued by any wrong, or inflicted vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence whatſoeuer: No no, that mans inocencie is not to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6608:15"/>wounded, with any, or all the practices of the vngodlie, who are forced in the end to retire all wearied, fainting and gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for breath.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. O Lord their wofull plight! they lie groueling vpon their bellies; they bray, grinne, and mutine with verie anger, bereaued of all power; for thou haſt broken, both their armes, teeth, and their iawes; and what not? So that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie weapon left them, is euen a will to continue in euill: A thing ſo hatefull vnto thy diuine nature and maieſtie. O <hi>Ephraims</hi> God! that thou ſhouldeſt take all their iniuties as done vnto thy ſelfe, and ſo in thy iuſtice throw the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines vpon them, vtterlie to roote out the memorie, of ſuch an vnmercifull, ſcoffing brood, from amongſt men.</p>
            <p n="60">
               <hi>LX.</hi> O Lord what a loue is this, when a father ſhall not ſpare his owne onelie ſonne, but giue him to bee ſlaine and tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to redeeme the miſerie of his ſlaue! wherefore, O moſt louing holie one of old; ſeeing that thou haſt pleaſed to frame and traine mee vp with thine owne hand, bought me with thy blood, and purified mee by thy mercie; forgiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now all my preſumptuous offences, cancell the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing of euidence againſt mee, purge my conſcience that it accuſe mee not; and ſince I deſire to forſake all the world to enioy thee, thy preſence, and promiſes; I do beſeech thee reiect mee neuer, for then will the wicked ſay, <hi>Where is his God, and the promiſe of his comming?</hi> and manie other preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall blaſphemous ſpeeches, againſt thy name.</p>
            <p n="61">LXI. O Lord I haue long ſince, and euen now doe ſacrifice my heart, conſecrate my affections, and deuote my thoughts vnto thee, violentlie plucking them out of the bottome of that euill heart of mine; ſo that my onlie deſire now is to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6608:16"/>ſerue thee faithfully with all my whole ſtrength, my ſoule and ſpirit, and to loue my neighbour as my verie ſelfe. But as it is not poſſible to write any thing vpon writing tables, vnleſſe that bee rubbed out, which was written before: Right ſo, (my mercifull God) vnleſſe thou purge and waſh this ſame old beſoiled contagion of my heart, it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to engraue thy word and will in it.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. Plucke vp therefore by the rootes thoſe cuſtomary pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of my wicked vncleane courſe, and according to thy gratious promiſes, <hi>Make me heare of ioy and gladnes of heart by earneſt of thy ſpirit:</hi> Aſſuring me that my requeſt ſtandeth among the Angels, tendered by the gronings of the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the name of the Redeemer, and ſhall haue a gratious anſwere. Heare therefore O Lord, my groanes and ſighes, which doe teſtifie thy goodnes, and doe publiſh thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Encreaſe my ſtrength and courage, that I may ſtraine my cries and euen mount vp vnto thee; and graciouſlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline vnto the ſame, that out of a chaunged heart, I may ſing a new ſong of prayſes vnto thee.</p>
            <p n="63">LXIII. Satiſfie me O Lord I beſeech thee in caſting downe all my ſinnes vnder thy feete, that no eye may bee able to ſee them by piercing through the ſame: for I doe not onely bluſh to think vpon them, but euen hate my ſelfe for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them: The remembrance thereof grieueth me; the times that I took very vngratiouſly therein, be as a very vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vnto my ſoule, and my thoughts are ſore wounded with the heauie repreſentation thereof.</p>
            <p n="64">LXIIII. Pardon and deliuer me therefore, mercifull Lord, who through frailty haue yeelded my ſelfe vnto the bondage of ſinne, and with the onely twincke of thine eie my manacles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6608:16"/>ſhall flye from my wreſts. For when I poore ſinner ſhal once fall downe and lift vp my thoughts heauie and ſad before thee, thou doeſt pittie me, heare and accompliſh all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and makeſt me enioy whatſoeuer J aske: For what is thy delight? <hi>But to fill the hungry with good things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">LXV. But herein I faile wofully, not for that thou changeſt thine ancient pittie and purpoſe, but becauſe I my ſelfe do keepe no couenant with thee. No no, I doe not that which I might verie well doe, to keepe in the ſweet warme worke of grace begunne in my heart, and affoorded vnto mee: whereupon thou mercifully Lord, art euen forced to let me feele the want of the comfort I had, and ſo J mournefullie and with baſhfulnes returne vnto thee, as the tiewant of the ſchoole doth to be hiſted at vpon his returne.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. For alaſſe, my moſt mercifull Lord, as I haue ſaid before, ſo againe and againe I teſtifie: It is my ſelfe that am an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemie to my ſelfe, by my fraile wandring, vanities and vnſtable hart, that in thy very care thou takeſt mee vppe and correcteſt me in the open ſchoole, by diſgrace thereof ſeeking to worke compunction, filiall feare and a more faithfull returne vnto thee my very ſweet heart, and to thy holy ſchoole. But alas I am ſtill weake and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, ſo that if thou ſhouldeſt heare my requeſt and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me when I aske pardone, without correction; alaſſe let all men iudge what this is elſe but to pray thee giue mee leaue to continue in ſinne ſtill Alas my Lord, my holy one, thou knoweſt with what greefe I ſet down this cenſure vpon my ſelfe and others; but I dare not but doe it faithfullie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I write vnto thee in the ſpirit of the ſecond righteous Adam, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aue vnto thee all redreſſe and pitty, euen in the ſhade of death: for thou wilt doe it in time vnto ſuch as are grieued with their frailties.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6608:17"/>
            <p n="67">LXVII. And therefore my mercifull Lord let not mee be ſhaken with the rods of thy ſchoole and academy: but giue mee to reioice in all the ſtripes of my ſtrayings, yea euen in the changes of my changes, which will keepe mee ſweete and acceptable, by the often ſcowring and purging of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent corruption, which is diffuſed and diſperſed through my verie marrowe.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. For otherwiſe running aſtray ſtill in a ſinfull ſecure dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous peace of my affections(ſuch as the world only hath) I ſhall grow like a puddle, infected with manie foule ſtremes and ſtinkes, in thy ſacred noſtrels: afflict mee therefore my gentle Lord, <hi>hold mee faſt behind and before, and lay thy hand vpon mee,</hi> euen with all my verie heart; for that which thy afflictions take from mee, is nothing but my vanities, and workes of ſin and Satan: for the nakeder I am before thee, the more beautifull euer, my gratious Lord.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. So that whatſoeuer thou laieſt vpon mee, it is onely to make eaſie the way vnto thy holie hill, thereto receiue ſanctification and holy moderation in all my conuerſation: for thou knoweſt both the daies and liues of all thoſe that depend vpon thee, and wilt guide them in thy waie, &amp; giue vnto them whatſoeuer is needfull: they ſhall lacke no good thing, but poſſeſſe all peace, plenty and ioy in their daies.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. For I know that all thy afflictions, as thoſe ſame happie roddes of thy ſchoole, they are euer in thy owne moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hands, and meaſured in all pittifull moderation, both in quantitie, qualitie, and continuance of time: for quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thou propineſt to each of thy poore wounded ſeruants,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6608:17"/>a cuppe and portion conuenient for his bruſing and incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſeaſe, <hi>whereunto no man can applie a plaſter but onelie thou the Lord alone.</hi> And as for qualitie; phyſicke muſt be a little bitter or elſe it is of no worth; yet therefore doeſt thou temper it with the blood of the immaculate lam be, the moſt happie Redeemer of the world, to make it both ſettle, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and heale the poore wounded creature.</p>
            <p n="71">LXXI. And as for time, thou giueſt but daies of triall and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; houres of tentation according to thy good pleaſure: and euen in this ſmal induring, neuer any Goldſmith did ſo watch ouer his gold in the fire that it waſted not, as thou tendeſt vpon thy children, that in due ſeaſon thou mighteſt draw them out. O that ſame ſweete zealous rebuke of the Lord Ieſus vnto Satan! <hi>Is not this a brand taken out of the fire? the Lord rebuke thee Satan, euen the Lord that hath choſen Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="72">LXXII. Thou haſt mercifull Lord made it knowne vnto me, that thy ſeruant <hi>Iaacob</hi> wreſtled with thee, no longer then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dawning of the day; and that thereby I may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my troubles haue an appointed time for reſt, <hi>that weeping may abide in the euening, but ioy commeth in the morning: though Shadrach Meſhach and Abednego be caſt into the fire, an Angel of thine owne preſence ſhall goe with them, and releeue them in due time:</hi> So that neither fire nor floodes ſhall harme thy afflicted ones, whom thou haſt called by their names.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. For whatſoeuer thou moſt mercifull Lord, doeſt exerciſe thy children withall, it is but to make them know that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir bleſſednes is prepared in an other place, and laide vp for them from eternitie; <hi>And no man ſhall take them out of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6608:18"/>Lambes hands;</hi> for thou Lord who gaueſt them vnto him art greater then all; and therefore in thoſe ſame very times, that thou goeſt away and leaueſt them to ſorrow, yet they ſhall poſſeſſe the inheritance whoſe riches is infinite: An inheritance which beeing diuided amongſt all the children, will continue ſound and whole for euer and euer, whoſe parts ſhall be as great as the whole inheritance.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIV. Make vs ſtrong therefore O Lord, and in admiration of ſuch a high and pretious price, to ſcorne all the vaine things in the world; all the countenances of men, and the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rage of perſecuting tyrants: For let <hi>Peter,</hi> who denied thee by occaſion of a weake woman, haue thy preſence with him, and he will auowe boldly, the crucified Lambe before thoſe who put him to death; ſo Lord ſhew vs the light of thy countenance, and no alteration ſhall diſmaie vs.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. Oh what a ſpectacle haſt thou made for mine eies to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! nay, I am now ſo aſſured of thy mercies, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by reaſon of the care I ſee thou haſt of mee; as, though I ſhould ſee the greateſt Armie that poſſiblie may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet would I not be afraid, but ſtand ſtill vpon the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable written word, and my owne happie experience of thy truth, power, and promiſes, which are euer yea, and amen.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. O Lord couer mee vnder the grace and fauour of Chriſt Ieſus; make his mercies my buckler and my ſhield, that I may learne and follow his ſteppes, and hope in nothing but thy gracious goodneſſe, ſpringing afreſh out of his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie renewed and fragrant obedience, ſtill orient in thy glorious face; that I may be euer zealous of his will, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the dropping and ſweating faintings of my afflictions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6608:18"/>may prepare and eſtabliſh mee, in the whole accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my ſanctification.</p>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. For the knowledge and obedience of thy will, my Lord, is all my verie whole deſire, and the thing which muſt lead me, and guide me, through the windings and turnings of the labyrinth of this mortallitie; for this ſame verie obedience of thy will, is the verie path-way vnto euerlaſting life, which I ſo inceſſantlie gape and wiſh for.</p>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. Reueale vnto mee therefore this thy will, and laie it vp in my ſoule, that I may there keepe it moſt deerelie, and in the midſt of the congregation, I may ſpeake of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe by an open changed and renewed conuerſation; rendring all holie acknowledgements of thanks and praiſes vnto thy name, and thereby bring many children vnto thee, to which onelie end I deſire to liue.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXJX. I know O Lord, that death is the penaltie of originall ſinne and diſobedience: but ſince I am now planting a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for thy delight, <hi>for thou ſaieſt, thy heart ſhall reioice when my mouth ſpeaketh righteous things:</hi> ſpare mee therefore my God, ſuffer me not to go downe all belowe, but euen at the mouth of darkenes and death, plucke mee out of danger; &amp; mercifull Lord bee content, with my humble abaſhed and melting heart, without impoſing penaltie for my deſerued thraldome.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. Heare therefore O Lord my ſighes, and take in good part my broken voice, which teſtifieth thy euerlaſting and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable mercies: and ſince thine eare is neuer ſhut vnto thoſe that call vpon thee ſincerelie, &amp; ſeeke thy face mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninglie,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6608:19"/>encline the ſame thy amiable face and countenance vnto mee: for all ſorts of felicities follow thy preſence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinualie; afford the ſame vnto me my deere God, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this wounded heart of mine, and ſay and ſpeake peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee: behold, I am readie to ſeeke thy face.</p>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. O Lord, thou haſt promiſed this mercie of thine, &amp; how often haſt thou from thy pittie ſuſtained mee, when I haue ſpoken neuer a word vnto thee? by hearing my ſecret thoughts or rather the ſighing deſires of the ſpirite, calling vpon thee for grace and ſtrength that I might be deliuered: How manie perils haue I paſſed, when I did not ſo much as regard thee, in the violent rage and ſway of my miſerable youth, euen by thine owne gentleneſſe and care ouer me?</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. For ſince thou art that vncreated word, which hath made all things which doe a parte of thy will, and thy will is a part of thy ſelfe: doth it not repreſent it ſelfe vnto mee as thy face, in ſuch beautifull and excellent lineaments of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie in the heauens and earth, as ſhine moſt brightlie in euerie part thereof, eſpecialie in the places of thy pure worſhip?</p>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. Alas what daie, time, or inſtant of my life, ſhould I ceaſe to be waile and ſorrow for my ſinnes, which haue ſo much eſtranged mee from thy grace, fauour, and familiaritie, which the humble and meeke ſorte haue with thee their God? whoſe armes are diſplaied ſtill, and euer calling, <hi>Come, ſee and taſt your reſt, and be wearie of your fruitles toiles:</hi> and when euer thou pleaſeſt to depart, to take view of our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſeeking care after thee; thou doeſt ſtill by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of thy wings, by a ſecret inſtinct of grace, to follow thee with our eies, calling come, come, and ſee.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:19"/>
            <p n="84">LXXXIV. O Lord my God, which from the beginning haſt reached out this carefull hand of thine vnto the afflicted, which haſt alwaies gathered into thy armes the oppreſſed, &amp; comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the iuſt vniuſtlie vexed; grant me O Lord both ſtrength and courage, that I may take my ſpirits againe vnto mee, which are halfe in a dead ſleepe and ſlumber, by the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall diſtractions and vnprofitable cogitations, which my long exile and baniſhment from my countrie (where I was able to haue done thee ſome little ſeruice, and ſhew loue vnto my neibours) hath made vſuall vnto mee.</p>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. Grant mercifull Lord, that I may be cheered to glorifie thee with all my heart and ſpirite, &amp; ſtrangle by the ſtrength of thy voice, the blaſphemies and vnreſt of the wicked, who goe about to defame thine honour, and make a net for my ſoule, by ſpeaking euill of thy equall, righteous, and moſt gentle yoake; and not beeing able to reach vnto thee, yet go about violentlie to ruſh vpon thoſe thy poore afflicted ones, who deſire to liue peaceablie, &amp; ſerue thee faithfully.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. Oh what ranſome ſhall I offer vnto thee for my election (whereby I haue aſſurance of a more quiet peaceable dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heereafter.) Alas, I confeſſe to my great griefe I haue not one good worke, neither cleane thought, but all adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated and defiled with inherent vnrighteouſnes, concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, ignorance, and with the contagion of a long au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daucious prouocation, by open tranſgreſſion in thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence: Shall I offer vnto thee the treaſures of the earth? no, hell is full of them. No no my mercifull Lord, I faithfullie beleeue thou thy ſelfe wilt bee the price of my redemption: <hi>Thou wilt deliuer thine owne bodie, to ranſome thy ſeruant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:20"/>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. Thou wilt put vpon thee and cloath thy ſelfe with the dolours of death, to giue mee the ſtate of immortallitie; for certainerie whereof, thou ſuſtainedſt thy hell heere, thy fathers wrath, agonies and bloudie ſweate, that! might appeare in thy preſence blameleſſe and without ſpot, to the praiſe of thy euerlaſting grace, for euermore Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6608:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
